<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title></title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head><del>A Moment's Ornament</del><lb></lb><add>The House of Mirth</add> </head>
         <p>By Edith Wharton</p>  
         <p rend="bold">BOOK I</p>
         <p>Key: <s type="bold">Scribner's </s>/ Manuscript</p>
         <div xml:id="chapter1">
            <pb facs="http://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/imgsrv/image?id=mdp.39015030597051;seq=57"/>
           
           <!-- lemma 1 -->
           
            <p n="scrib">Selden paused in surprise.
              In the afternoon rush of the Grand Central Station 
              his eyes had been refreshed by the sight of Miss Lily Bart.</p>
            
            <p n="ms"><hi>Hensley</hi> paused in surprise.
              In the afternoon rush of the Grand Central Station his eyes had been refreshed by
              the sight of <del>a tall &amp; trimly tailored figure, with bright hair under a feather hat. </del><add>Miss Lily Hurst.</add></p>
            
           <!-- lemma 2 -->
            
            <p n="scrib">It was a Monday in early September, and he was returning to his work from a hurried dip into the country; 
              but what was Miss Bart doing in town at that season? If she had appeared to be catching a train, 
              he might have inferred that he had come on her in the act of transition between one and another of the country-houses which 
              disputed her presence after the close of the Newport season; but her desultory air perplexed him.
              She stood apart from the crowd, letting it drift by her to the platform or the street, and wearing an air of irresolution 
              which might, as he surmised, be the mask of a very definite purpose.It struck him at once that 
              she was waiting for some one, but he hardly knew why the idea arrested him. There was nothing 
              new about Lily Bart, yet he could never see her without a faint movement of interest: it was characteristic of her that 
              she always roused speculation, that her simplest acts seemed the result of far-reaching intentions.</p>
            
            <p n="ms">It was <del>an afternoon </del><del>a Monday </del><add>a Thursday in mid-September,</add> and he was returning to 
              <del>his week's</del> work from a <del>Sunday in Long Island</del> <add>hurried dip into the country</add>; 
              but what was <del>Juliet Hurst</del> <add>Miss Bart</add> doing in town at that season? If she 
              <del>had the appeared</del> <del>seemed</del> <add>appeared</add> to be catching a train, 
              he might have inferred that he had come <del>upon</del> <add>on</add> her in the act of transition between one and another of the country-houses which 
              disputed her presence after <add place="above">close of the</add> Newport season<del> was over</del>; 
              but her desultory air perplexed him.
              She stood in detached indifference, letting the <del>hot</del> crowd drift by her to the platform <del>of</del> or the street, and wearing an air of irresolution 
              which might, as he surmised, be the mask of a very definite purpose. It <del>occurred to him</del> struck him at once that 
              she <del>might be</del> was waiting <del>to meet</del> for some one, but he hardly knew why the <del>conjecture interested</del> idea arrested him.
              There was nothing <del>There was nothing</del>
              new about <del>Juliet Hurst</del> Lily Bart, yet he could never see her without a <del>vague</del> faint movement of <del>curiosity</del> interest: 
              it was characteristic of her that 
              she always roused speculation, that her simplest acts seemed the <del>expression of a complex intention</del> result of complex intentions.</p>
            
           <!-- lemma 3 -->
            
            <p n="scrib">An impulse of curiosity made him turn out of his direct line to the door, and stroll past her.
              He knew that if she did not wish to be seen she would contrive to elude him; and it amused him to think of putting her skill to the test.</p>
         
            <p n="ms">An <del>a random</del> impulse <add place="above">of curiosity</add> made <del>Hensley</del> <add>Selden</add> turn out of his direct line to the door, and stroll past her 
              <del>as she stood in vague expectancy</del>.
              <add place="above">He knew that if</add> <del>If</del> she did not wish to be seen <del>, he knew that</del> she would <del>easily contrive to</del>
              <add place="above">contrive to</add> elude him; and it amused him to think of putting her <add place="above">ingenuity</add> ingenuity to the test.</p>
           
           <!-- lemma 4 -->
           
            <p n="scrib">"Mr. Selden--what good luck!"</p>
           
            <p n="ms">"Mr. <del>Hensley</del> <add place="above">Selden</add>--what good luck!"</p>
           
           <!-- lemma 5 -->
           
            <p n="scrib">She came forward smiling, eager almost, in her resolve to intercept him. One or two persons, in brushing past them, lingered to look; 
              for Miss Bart was a figure to arrest even the suburban traveller rushing to his last train.  </p>
           
            <p n="ms">She <del>advanced</del> <add>came forward</add> smiling, <del>almost eager</del><add> eager almost</add>, in her <del>determination</del>
              <add>resolve</add> to intercept him. One or two persons, in brushing past them, lingered to look; 
              for <hi>Miss Hurst</hi> was a figure to arrest even the suburban <del>traveller</del> rushing to his last train.  </p>
           
           <!-- lemma 6 -->
           
            <p n="scrib">Selden had never seen her more radiant. Her vivid head, relieved against the dull tints of the crowd, 
              made her more conspicuous than in a ball-room, and under her dark hat and veil she regained the girlish smoothness, 
              the purity of tint, that she was beginning to lose after eleven years of late hours and indefatigable dancing. 
              Was it really eleven years, Selden found himself wondering, and had she indeed reached the nine-and-twentieth birthday 
              with which her rivals credited her?</p>
         
            <p n="ms"><del>Hensley</del> <add place="above">Selden</add> <del>thought he</del> had never seen her more radiant. 
              Her vivid head, relieved against the dull <del>flesh</del> tints of the crowd, 
              made her more conspicuous than in a ball-room, &amp; <del>in with the vague light faintly-diffused light of the semi-twilight of the waiting room</del> 
              <add place="above">under her dark hat and veil</add> she regained the girlish smoothness, 
              the purity of tint, that she was beginning to lose after eleven years of late hours and indefatigable dancing. 
              Was it really eleven years, Selden found himself wondering, and had she indeed reached the nine-and-twentieth birthday 
              with which her <del>friends charged</del> <add>rivals credited</add> her?</p>
           
           <!-- lemma 7 -->
           
            <p n="scrib">"What luck!" she repeated. "How nice of you to come to my rescue!"</p>
           
            <p n="ms">"What luck!" she repeated. "How nice of you to come to my rescue!"</p>
           
           <!-- lemma 8 -->
           
            <p n="scrib">He responded joyfully that to do so was his mission in life, and asked what form the rescue was to take.</p>
         
            <p n="ms"><del>He responded joyfully that he was there for that purpose, &amp; asked from what monster she wished he could deliver her.</del>
              <del>"Oh,</del> He responded <add place="above">joyfully</add> that to do so was his mission in life, and asked <del>joyfully</del> 
              what he could <add place="above">do for her.</add></p>
           
           <!-- lemma 9 -->
           
            <p n="scrib">"Oh, almost any--even to sitting on a bench and talking to me.  One sits out a cotillion--why not sit out a train? 
              It isn't a bit hotter here than in Mrs. Van Osburgh's conservatory--and some of the women are not a bit uglier."  </p>
           
            <p n="ms">"Oh, almost <hi>anything</hi>--even to sitting on a bench and talking to me.  One sits out a cotillion--why not <add place="above">sit out</add> a train? 
              It isn't a bit hotter <add place="above">here</add> than in Mrs. Van Osburgh's conservatory--and some of the women are not a bit uglier."  </p>
           
           <!-- lemma 10 -->
           
            <p n="scrib">She broke off, laughing, to explain that she had come up to town from Tuxedo, on her way to the Gus Trenors' at Bellomont, 
              and had missed the three-fifteen train to Rhinebeck.</p>
           
            <p n="ms">She broke off, laughing, to explain that she had come up to town from Tuxedo, <del>&amp;</del> on her way to the Gus Trenors' at Bellomont, 
              and had missed the three-fifteen train to Rhinebeck.</p>
           
           <!-- lemma 11 -->
           
            <p n="scrib">"And there isn't another till half-past five." She consulted the little jewelled watch among her laces.  
              "Just two hours to wait. And I don't know what to do with myself. 
              My maid came up this morning to do some shopping for me, and was to go on to Bellomont at one o'clock, 
              and my aunt's house is closed, and I don't know a soul in town." She glanced plaintively about the station. 
              "It is hotter than Mrs. Van Osburgh's, after all. If you can spare the time, do take me somewhere for a breath of air."</p>
           
            <p n="ms">"And there isn't another till half-past five." She consulted <del>her</del> <add place="above">the</add> little jewelled watch 
              <add place="above">among her laces.</add> "Just two hours to wait. And I don't know <del>where on earth to go</del> 
              <add place="above">what to do with myself.</add> 
              My maid came up this morning to do some shopping for me, &amp; <del>of course she must have</del> 
              was to <del>take the one o'clock train to Rhinebeck</del><add place="above">go on to Bellomont at one o'clock,</add> 
              and my aunt's house is closed, and I don't know a soul in town." She glanced plaintively about the station. 
              "It is hotter than Mrs. Van Osburgh's, <del>after all</del> <add place="above">after all.</add> If you can spare the time, do take me somewhere for a breath of air."</p>
           
           <!-- lemma 12 -->
           
            <p n="scrib">He declared himself entirely at her disposal: the adventure struck him as diverting. As a spectator, 
              he had always enjoyed Lily Bart; and his course lay so far out of her orbit that it amused him to be drawn 
              for a moment into the sudden intimacy which her proposal implied.</p>
           
            <p n="ms">He declared himself entirely at her disposal: <del>&amp;hav</del> the adventure struck him as <del>rather amusing</del> 
              <del n="above">entertaining</del> <add place="above">diverting.</add> <add>As a spectator he had</add> <del>
              he had</del> always enjoyed <del>Juliet</del> <add place="above">Lily</add> <hi>Hurst</hi> <del>as a looker on</del>; and his course lay so far out of her orbit that it amused him to be drawn 
              for a moment into the sudden intimacy which her proposal implied.</p>
          
           
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>