<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="mirth.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication information</p>        
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <head><del>A Moment's Ornament</del><add>The House of Mirth</add> </head>
         <p>By</p>
         <p>Edith Wharton</p>
         
         <p rend="bold">BOOK I</p>
         <div type="chapter">
            <pb facs="http://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/imgsrv/image?id=mdp.39015030597051;seq=57"/>
            
            <p rend="indent" n="p1"><s type="#scrib" n="0001">Selden paused in surprise.</s>
               <s type="#scrib" n="0002">In the afternoon rush of the Grand Central Station 
                  his eyes had been refreshed by the sight of Miss Lily Bart.</s></p>
            
            <p rend="indent" n="p1"><s type="#ms" n="0001">Hensley paused in surprise.</s>
               <s type="#ms" n="0002">In the afternoon rush of the Grand Central Station his eyes had been refreshed by
                  the sight of <del>a tall &amp; trimly tailored figure, with bright hair under a feather hat. </del><add>Miss Lily Hurst.</add></s></p>
            
            <p n="p2"><s type="#scrib" n="0003">It was a Monday in early September, and he was returning to his work from a hurried dip into the country; 
               but what was Miss Bart doing in town at that season?</s><s type="#scrib" n="0004">If she had appeared to be catching a train, 
               he might have inferred that he had come on her in the act of transition between one and another of the country-houses which 
               disputed her presence after the close of the Newport season; but her desultory air perplexed him.</s><s type="#scrib" n="0005">
               She stood apart from the crowd, letting it drift by her to the platform or the street, and wearing an air of irresolution 
               which might, as he surmised, be the mask of a very definite purpose.</s><s type="#scrib" n="0006">It struck him at once that 
               she was waiting for some one, but he hardly knew why the idea arrested him.</s><s type="#scrib" n="0007">There was nothing 
               new about Lily Bart, yet he could never see her without a faint movement of interest: it was characteristic of her that 
               she always roused speculation, that her simplest acts seemed the result of far-reaching intentions.</s></p>
            
            <p n="p2"><s type="#ms" n="0003">It was <del>an afternoon </del><del>a Monday </del><hi>a Thursday in mid-September,</hi> and he was returning to 
               <del>his week's</del> work from a <del>Sunday in Long Island</del> hurried dip into the country; 
               but what was <del>Juliet Hurst</del> Miss Bart doing in town at that season?</s><s type="#ms" n="0004">If she 
               <del>had the appeared</del> <del>seemed</del> appeared to be catching a train, 
               he might have inferred that he had come <del>upon</del> on her in the act of transition between one and another of the country-houses which 
               disputed her presence after <add type="above">close of the</add> Newport season<del> was over</del>; 
               but her desultory air perplexed him.</s><s type="#ms" n="0005">
               She stood in detached indifference, letting the <del>hot</del> crowd drift by her to the platform <del>of</del> or the street, and wearing an air of irresolution 
               which might, as he surmised, be the mask of a very definite purpose.</s><s type="#ms" n="0006">It <del>occurred to him</del> struck him at once that 
               she <del>might be</del> was waiting <del>to meet</del> for some one, but he hardly knew why the <del>conjecture interested</del> idea arrested him.</s>
               <s type="#ms" n="0007">There was nothing <del>There was nothing</del>
               new about <del>Juliet Hurst</del> Lily Bart, yet he could never see her without a <del>vague</del> faint movement of <del>curiosity</del> interest: 
               it was characteristic of her that 
               she always roused speculation, that her simplest acts seemed the <del>expression of a complex intention</del> result of complex intentions.</s></p>
            
            <p n="p3"><s type="#scrib" n="0008">An impulse of curiosity made him turn out of his direct line to the door, and stroll past her.</s>
               <s type="scrib" n="0009">He knew that if she did not wish to be seen she would contrive to elude him; and it amused him to think of putting her skill to the test.</s></p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
